[Music]
denmark ended up canceling its saturated
fat tax on meat and dairy and shelving
their sugar tax because the farming and
food company interest claimed too many
jobs would be lost if people ate
healthier
apparently a healthy economy was more
important than a healthy citizenry
ironically the fact tax was abolished
just when evidence of the effects
started to appear the intake of
saturated fat among danish customers
from some meat and dairy products was
declining
but not from sour cream the public ended
up eating so much more low-fat sour
cream that ended up outweighing the
smaller reduction in high-fat sour cream
so you always have to think about the
unintended consequences
if incentives have people swapping out
sugary cookies for salty chips for
example it might not be doing the
public's health many favors
one field study of attacks on soda found
that you can drop soft drink purchases
but households may just end up
buying more beer
another study found that calorie
labeling of sugary drinks ironically led
to an increase in consumption presumed
to be because the consumers may have
previously overestimated their calorie
content
stark warnings about the risks of
unintended negative consequences of
obesity targeted health policies are
trumpeted by those with ties to the
likes of coca-cola craft pepsico wrigley
red bull the world sugar research
organization national cattlemen's
association mars
and corn syrup giant archer daniels
midland and that's just a single
scientist
the concern about unintended
consequences shouldn't paralyze our
efforts but should serve up a healthy
dose of humility when considering policy
proposals
how about releasing a video game for
kids that promotes fruit
sounds good right well what do you think
happened when kids were sat down in
front of bowls of fruit and candy and
randomized to play one of three
different computer advert games
advertising game hybrids incorporating
product placements promoting either
candy fruit or toys the pro candy game
group ate more candy but disappointingly
the pro fruit group didn't eat more
fruit
but then it gets interesting they ate
more candy in the fruit game too
compared to the toy promotion control
group having a kid play a video game
promoting fruit led them to eat more
candy
presumably both the candy and fruit
games just made them think about food
and they naturally gravitated to their
preferred snack
one of the most fascinating phenomena i
came across was the boomerang effect of
remedy messaging one might presume that
the advertising of smoking cessation
aids like nicotine gum would help make
quitting easier after all the vast
majority of smokers want to quit and so
availing them of helpful options
couldn't help but help right
instead such remedy marketing can create
a vicarious get out of jail free card
that ends up reinforcing risky behavior
exposure to nicotine replacement product
advertising was found to undermine
quitting intentions especially among the
heaviest smokers the very ones who
needed it the most
the thought is that smokers may
subconsciously interpret the remedy as
evidence that the hazards of smoking are
more manageable hence less risky and
thereby help to justify their habit
you can see how easily this would
translate to the weight loss arena
previously i explored how self-licensing
could cause those taking slimming
supplements to inadvertently eat more
but just exposure to a fat fighting pill
advertisement appeared to have a similar
type of effect so even when companies
are ostensibly selling health rather
than disease they still may be
inadvertently making the problem worse
in the marketplace there's just no
incentive for risk avoidance messaging
nobody makes money selling just say no
unless it can be somehow linked to
saleable products and services
a policy in france where burgers now
outsell baguettes may represent an
interesting real world example of this
counter-intuitive remedy messaging
effect industry lobbying morphed a
valiant effort to ban the advertising of
junk into a mandate for preventive
health messaging on junk food
advertisements
so now on products like lay's chips sava
puli roti
chicken flavored potato chips you'll see
messages like
i'm not gonna try to pronounce that in
french but basically for your health
practice regular physical activity hey
sounds good right but any time an
industry agrees to a regulation one
should get skeptical as to its
effectiveness
to see if such messaging might lead to a
boomerang effect research subjects were
randomized to view a big mac
advertisement with or without the
preventive health message eat five
fruits and vegetables a day
i mean hey wouldn't it be great if
mcdonald's was forced to advertise
healthy food
the participants then filled out some bs
questionnaire and before they left were
allowed to choose one of two mcdonald's
coupons as a reward for their
participation a free sunday or free bag
of fruit
guess who was more likely to pick the
fruit
only one in three of those who just saw
the straight burger advertisement chose
the fruit over the sunday but that
number fell to only one in six among
those who've been prompted to eat
healthier
let that sink in for a second isn't that
crazy the absence of the health message
doubled the choice of the healthy snack
the health message made things worse
this may be the remedy messaging
boomerang effect in action by
simultaneously offering a temptation
with a reminder about how they can dig
themselves out later justifies the
excuse to indulge
subconsciously it may give the chickeny
chip eater the rationalization that they
can just work it off the next day even
if the next day at the gym never comes
the advised antidote to avoid
justification effects is to instead use
negative framing instead of offering a
way out to compensate for indulging just
this one time cautionary messages may be
more effective
for example
you know on your next ham and cheese or
chocolate filled croissant
a message like for your health avoid
foods that are too fatty too sweet or
too salty now that's a message
for which i doubt li mcdonald's would be
as enthusiastic
learning about this rebound effect has
made me reflect about my work on
nutritionfacts.org
distilled into how not to die
doesn't get much more remedy messaging
than that if we can get such dramatic
benefits with diet and lifestyle changes
so late in life in such short amount of
time why can't we just live lives of
gluttony and sloth and then around 50 or
so clean up our acts
the reason is because it may be too late
our first symptom may be our last
most people know the number one killer
of both men and women in the united
states is heart disease
what people may not know though is that
according to the american heart
association for the majority of
americans that die of heart disease
their first symptom occurs not years
before they die but literally minutes
before they die
sudden cardiac death is the first
manifestation of heart disease for the
majority of individuals particularly
among women meaning you have no idea you
even had heart disease until you're
literally dying from it
heart disease reversal is great but
that's why prevention is the key when it
comes to sudden death announcement
prevention truly is worth more than a
pound of cure because there is no cure
for dead
[Music]
you